<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Life | Bobbie's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2021-02-14T22:34:12-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bowei "Bobbie" Wu .]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Underestimating My Ignorance]]></title>
    <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2021/02/14/underestimating-my-ignorance/"/>
    <updated>2021-02-14T22:23:50-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2021/02/14/underestimating-my-ignorance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>“Being ignorant is bad.” So would most people think. I try hard to be more knowledgeable and I am still ashamed of my own ignorance oftentimes. But I am also learning more and more about the positive power of ignorance — a power that has been underestimated.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>Thanks to last year’s COVID lockdown, I had the chance to concentrate on research without distractions. I was fortunate enough to make some discoveries, which I thought was a huge breakthrough. After submitting some papers, a few months later I found out that I have in fact overlooked some closely related work in the literature. One of my results looked less great given the existing work, although it was still a nice progress.</p>

<p>While this has been a humbling experience, it was also inspiring: I wouldn’t have been so optimistic if I knew how long a journey the pioneers have traveled; I might have lost my faith and given up early if I knew all the failed attempts by other people. It was exactly my ignorance that had given me the courage to attack the open problems and the hope to keep pushing. Luckily, I eventually bumped into paths and territories that others have overlooked which led to my destination.</p>

<p>As Alain Connes once wrote, the initial phase of making new math discoveries “requires a kind of protection of one’s ignorance.” Sometimes, ignorance “frees people from reverence for authority and allows them to rely on their intuition.” In the same spirit, Steve Jobs also told people to “stay hungry, stay foolish.” Perhaps all intellectuals, including academics and industrial innovators, can use some protections of ignorance.</p>

<p>We like to be well-prepared before going into a challenging adventure. But knowing all the failed journeys of other people, knowing that even some brave and strong peers had failed their missions, can actually paralyse you into inaction. In fact, exploring the math world doesn’t require your having “full knowledge” about any field. Nobody ever knew “enough.” Once you know a minimum amount of knowledge that allows you to survive, you can start your journey.</p>

<p>“Whatever the origin of one’s journey, one day, if one walks far enough, one is bound to stumble on a well-known town: for instance, elliptic functions, modular forms, or zeta functions.” This is another quote from Alain Connes, which resonates with me deeply. There is no single path to knowledge, we can be free to explore our own paths and not be ashamed of knowing too little about all other possible paths. Be brave and keep pushing, once in a while we will meet with other adventurers in one of those famous mathematical towns.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reaction and Creation Are Antonyms]]></title>
    <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2021/01/17/reaction-and-creation-are-antonyms/"/>
    <updated>2021-01-17T20:06:52-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2021/01/17/reaction-and-creation-are-antonyms</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>… and anagrams. (How cute!)</p>

<h3 id="the-reactionary-approach">The Reactionary Approach</h3>

<p>The reactionary approach seems to be a default setting of human behavior: people react only when something undesirable happens. Consequently, people have to react every single time something undesirable happens. This is apparently so in politics (especially prominent in 2020). But you can observe reactionary behaviors in all other domains.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>For example, parents and teachers often react against technology. It’s quite typical to hear things like “Turn off the video game!” or “Put down your phone!” or “No electronics in class!”</p>

<p>Another common example is doing presentations. Now that most presentations are done with slides, you can find a lot of reactionary advice such as “Don’t put everything on one slide” or “Don’t include irrelavant pictures or animations” or “Don’t use illegible fancy fonts.”</p>

<p>Taking a reactionary approach is totally fine when the problem you are dealing with is simple (like replenishing your toilet paper) or a one-off thing (like repairing a flat tire). For more complex and constantly evolving problems, such as education and technology, taking a reactionary approach is like playing a never-ending whac-a-mole game: you banned gaming, they turned to their phones; you banned phones, they turned to weed and drugs. It never solves the real problem. It is exhausting and can be harmful to your relationships. Maybe we can take a more systematic approach.</p>

<h3 id="the-creationary-approach">The Creationary Approach</h3>

<p>What makes me happy is that more and more creative people are taking on the task of improving education with technology.</p>

<p>An early example is the Khan Academy. Khan started by making videos to teach some of the school classes online. This seemingly simple approach enables what’s called the self-paced learning: instead of being forced to sit and listen in class, students can pick their own time to watch the videos; instead of feeling embarrassed to ask questions, students can just replay the part where they were lost. The traditional way of learning is to attend lectures in class and do the homework after. But with the video lectures, students can now watch them at home and do the homework in class (i.e., tutoring). Learning becomes more engaging and more human.</p>

<p>This is what I’d like to call a <strong>creationary approach</strong>. I see “reactionary” and “creationary” as antonyms (and they are anagrams!):</p>

<ul>
  <li>A reactionary approach is to react against something only when an undesirable result happens.</li>
  <li>A creationary approach is to create something so that desirable results can happen.</li>
</ul>

<p>Over the past decades, I am seeing more and more creationary people teaching math creatively with the help of technology. Just to name a few of them:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Burkard Polster (channel: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC1_uAIS3r8Vu6JjXWvastJg">Mathologer</a>) is an engaging story-teller. He presents interesting maths that are not taught in school, which can really broaden your view.</li>
  <li>Grant Sanderson (channel: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCYO_jab_esuFRV4b17AJtAw">3Blue1Brown</a>) created a <a href="https://github.com/3b1b/manim">math animation engine</a> to make inspiring animations that introduce cool maths to a general audience.</li>
  <li>Cliff Stoll (appeared many times on the <a href="https://youtube.com/playlist?list=PLt5AfwLFPxWJeBhzCJ_JXdaIXi_YJl7Bh">Numberphile</a>), among many other creative things, has made strange pieces of glassware to teach topology. (He is also a <a href="https://slashdot.org/comments.pl?sid=1981970&amp;cid=35112450">creative science teacher</a>. I highly recommend listening to his <a href="https://youtu.be/lxdcBD4ppF0">interview</a> with the Numberphile.)</li>
  <li>The recent <a href="https://computationalthinking.mit.edu/Fall20/">Computational Thinking</a> course is a collaboration between MIT and the Julia Programming community. It is a terrific attempt to push the limit of distance learning during the pandemic.</li>
</ul>

<p>It is people like these who have given me a lot of hope and excitement about the future of education.</p>

<h3 id="be-creationary">Be Creationary</h3>

<p>In our daily life, we often run into a whac-a-mole lifestyle, too. People go on a diet to lose weight multiple times a year. People try to quit smoking many times in their life. People are making the same New Year Resolutions every year.</p>

<p>To take a creationary approach to life means to make choices based on what you are <em>for</em> rather than what you are <em>against</em>.</p>

<p>One trick I often use is to create connections between the things I love doing with the things I think I should do. For example, I enjoy doing exercises because I love listening to podcasts at the same time. I enjoy eating healthy because healthy foods are delicious and it allows me to focus on my research problems for longer without getting fatigue easily. Once these connections become my habits and instincts, doing the “hard” thing feels effortless.</p>

<p>Of course, taking a creationary approach is hard. It is not always easy to know what you are for; it can be very hard to find your purpose; being creative may not always give you the desired result. But I also believe that creativity is something that you can train for: be aware that you can always choose creation over reaction, allow yourself more chances to experiment and to fail, learn from creative people and enjoy their company. Sooner or later, you will encounter your own serendipity.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making Small Changes in Life]]></title>
    <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2021/01/02/making-small-changes-in-life/"/>
    <updated>2021-01-02T02:12:19-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2021/01/02/making-small-changes-in-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday was the last day of 2020 and the first day that was cold and rainy and windy all day since I resumed exercising every day. I had been expecting such a day.</p>

<p>At the beginning of December after reading a <a href="https://www.stevepavlina.com/blog/2020/12/pondering-a-365-day-challenge-for-2021/">blog post</a>, I finally decided to do a 365-Day Challenge for the year of 2021: running every day for at least 15 minutes a day. Then I decided to start right away even if it was still 2020, because why not. This may sound like a joke to some people because, seriously, how is this even a “challenge”?</p>

<!--more-->

<p>As someone who has done a few short-term challenges, I know that there are always something unexpected in the way that can ruin your plan. If you do a <a href="https://www.stevepavlina.com/blog/2005/04/30-days-to-success/">30-Day Challenge</a>, one most important point is not that how easy or hard it is to do it on a given day, but that if you skipped even one day, you failed. When a challenge lasts as long as 365 days, there are plenty of bad things that could just happen, say, on the 113th day and then all the things you did during the first 112 days are wasted.</p>

<p>For my own challenge, I have imagined days when I will be too busy and stressful meeting a deadline, or days when the weather is just too bad, or days when I have been driving all day and feel too tired to do anything, or days when I have traveled to a strange place that could be unsafe to run outside. I am sure there are many more situations that I just can’t imagine yet.</p>

<h3 id="short-term-challenges">Short-term challenges</h3>

<p>Since 2018, I have done a few short-term challenges – sometimes with a purpose and sometimes just to bring some new ingredients into life. I started with a 30-Day Vegan challenge; then I went on to do a 30-Day Pescatarian challenge which wound up lasted almost 5 months. Now I am back to omnivorous, but with more knowledge about different dietary options and how it feels to be a practitioner. In general, I become more mindful with how different foods affect my body and mind, and I am eating much healthier than before the dietary challenges.</p>

<p>One thing that was unexpected while eating vegan was the experience of being a minority. Growing up in China I have never been a member of a minority group. After I came to the US, I did meet racist strangers in a few occasions throughout these years, but in general I am in academic environments that have always been welcoming and never made me feel like a minority. But during my 30 days of eating vegan, the restaurants I went to often made me feel that I am a trouble to them through their reactions, including some major restaurants that do provide vegetarian options. In order to feel more comfortable, every time I decided to eat out I had to do more investigations and select appropriate restaurants. Most of the time I just cook my own food. (On the good side, I did discover some vegan friendly cuisines, like Indian and Mediterranean, which are very enjoyable.)</p>

<p>I also did a 30-Day Swimming challenge for which I swam for an hour a day everyday. I did it because there was a year or two during my time at Michigan when I stopped exercising completely. I remember it was one sunny day in the winter in early 2018, I finally went for a swim after a long time. I can never forget the moment when I pushed open the door and came out of the gym, a breeze of cool air flowed into my chest. “How refreshing!” I said to myself. That was a feeling I had missed for so long. At that day, I started and completed the swimming challenge. Then I was motivated enough that I continued to do exercise, either swimming or running for at least an hour, 5 to 6 times every week, until the pandemic hit in the March of 2020.</p>

<p>There is one important lesson I learned from making these small changes in life: you must reinforce these changes by associating them with immediate rewards; never rely on grit and pervseverance since those are guaranteed to wane overtime and you are bound to fail that way; losing weight is such a reward that comes so late that most people with that goal fail. Here are some examples of immediate rewards that worked for me:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Find shows or programs that you love, and listen to them when working out. I particularly liked listening to podcasts when I am running. (Lately I am listening to NPR’s Hidden Brain and The Numberphile Podcast.)</li>
  <li>Pay attention to your feelings, however small they are. When I eat more veges and less sugars, I typically feel more agile and can stay focused for longer periods. When I am done exercising, I feel happier, more awaked and alert.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="day-challenge">365-Day Challenge</h3>

<p>I have stopped being active for 9 months since the COVID lockdown in March. So finally at the beginning of December, I decided to do the 365-Day Challenge for the year of 2021 and also started running again right away.</p>

<p>All went well for almost a month. Then there came December 31th of 2020, the day that I have so many perfect excuses to skip it.</p>

<p>It was cold and rainy the whole day (even raining hail in the afternoon); I had invited a few people for a gathering that night and had to do grocery shopping during the day; I had planned to work a little on my research in the morning; most “importantly,” it was still 2020 and my 365-Day Challenge did not “officially” start until the next day.</p>

<p>Given all the circumstances, this is a day I have imagined from the beginning. I decided that if I skip this day, I won’t be able to convince myself that I can still complete every single day of the following 365 days. So I kept an eye on the weather forecast and just went out once the rain temporarily stopped. It was freezing and windy outside, the street was empty and quiet. Shortly after I began running, it started to rain again. When I got home, my face and hands were numb but I was very happy. Interestingly, the <a href="https://omny.fm/shows/hidden-brain/a-creature-of-habit">podcast</a> I was listening to that day talked about building habits.</p>

<p>Now, my 365 days begin. Thanks to that rainy day, I am quite confident about completing it this year while working on many different things.</p>

<h3 id="update-jan-10-2021">Update Jan 10, 2021</h3>

<p>Today, it snowed in Austin! Going out for a run is actually not hard for me at this point – I think I have successfully built this into my habit in the past 30 days.</p>

<p>I have taken some photos of the snow. Although such snow is no big deal for someone who has lived in Michigan, it is definitely a rare event in Texas!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/blog_figures/austin_snow1.jpg" width="400"></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/blog_figures/austin_snow2.jpg" width="400"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Everybody Said That 2020 Was Bad]]></title>
    <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2020/12/27/everybody-said-that-2020-was-bad/"/>
    <updated>2020-12-27T16:40:06-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2020/12/27/everybody-said-that-2020-was-bad</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I feel like writing something before 2020 ends. Since this has been a special year, I will write two versions of it.</p>

<h3 id="version-i">Version I</h3>

<p>This has been a special year because everybody said that it was bad. The COVID pandemic suddenly exploded and completely changed our way of living. People may still remember that this is the same year when Kobe Bryant died from an accident, but it feels like this happened an eternity ago — as with everything else that happened before lockdown.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>The pandemic seemed “inevitable” in hindsight. For decades people like Nassim Taleb and Bill Gates had been warning about such an event as being a necessary outcome of our world getting ever more connected. Yet, when it finally happened, it has hit us so quickly and strongly that nobody was prepared. Early on, many people wishfully thought that it would just disappear quickly and magically somehow; then people thought that it might only last for a few months; eventually, people are disappointed to find out that we end up practicing the lockdown lifestyle for the rest of 2020 and may well be doing it for a good part of 2021. Currently, the first wave of vaccines arrived and are being produced and distributed; however, a second wave of outbreak is also hitting hard on the US, Europe, and many other places in the world. The virus has mutated and we still don’t see a clear way out of this extended battle.</p>

<p>This is the mainstream and social media’s version of “This has been a special year.” Everybody has been living an extraordinarily bad year according to this narrative. We are under the constant bombardment of bad news.</p>

<p>I would like to take a break for a moment, and remind myself that nobody’s life is the same. After all, we are individuals living our own life and having our own experience. It is true that everybody was hit by the pandemic one way or another, but it cannot be true that we all have the same experience and feelings.</p>

<p>We can’t control what comes at us, but we can decide how we perceive and respond to those events. (And it is probably wise to cut oneself off from the media most of the time, too.)</p>

<p>So I would like to write a second version of “This has been a special year” that is particular to myself, because surely everybody has their own special year.</p>

<h3 id="version-ii">Version II</h3>

<p>This has been a special year for me, because it is meaningful to myself in many ways.</p>

<ul>
  <li>I began this year traveling to New Orleans and Houston. This has been my first road trip in the south since I came to Austin, and I liked the culture and history of those places.</li>
  <li>After the lockdown in March, I was able to entirely focus on my research projects. Luckily, I had made some important breakthroughs, which turned into one of the most meaningful and rewarding experience in my life. I realized being an academic is a previlage during the pandemic and I am very grateful for that.</li>
  <li>I had been in a long distance relationship. But because of the pandemic, I get to spend most of this year living with my girlfriend. Her emotional support has been vital during this time. I am truly grateful for all the precious time and memories we had together so far.</li>
  <li>I used to swim 5 to 6 times a week before the pandemic. But since March, I stopped exercising completely and stayed this way for the past 9 months. I was clearly feeling worse with my body and realizing that I had been taking my health for granted. So finally this month, I decided to return to the habit of daily exercise. So far, I am enjoying running outside everyday while listening to podcasts — I know this would have been much harder if I were still in Michigan’s cold winter!</li>
</ul>

<p>At the beginning of the COVID pandemic, my parents from China were very worried about my situation in the US. I assured them that I was fine and had things to be busy with; I remember I explicitly told my parents: “This pandemic will one day come to an end and become a past memory. I don’t want to wake up that day just to realize that I have wasted my time in the entire year of 2020, doing nothing but doomscrolling through bad news all day long.” I would like to thank my past self for delivering this powerful message and staying focused on the more important and meaningful things.</p>

<p>To be fair though, I did take the COVID seriously from early on (maybe even a little paranoid). Back in January when everything was unclear about the disease, and when people in China were still planning to celebrate the Lunar New Year, I already bought my parents some masks and told them to stay away from crowds and wash hands. I recall that just a few days after I bought those masks for my parents, all the masks were sold out on Taobao or any other Chinese e-commerce platforms. No joke, it was frightening. After the pandemic hit the US, “don’t let my parents worry for me” had been one of my biggest motivations to stay healthy. I very much hope that the situation would end soon in 2021 that I can be meeting with my family and friends and traveling again.</p>

<p>I have not updated my blog for a year now and I would like to get back to writing a little more often. I originally planned to start writing after the New Year. But the lockdown experience made it clear to me that many concepts (such as the “new year”) are merely human constructs — they can be sometimes a mental obstruction when you want to start something new. So, to break the “wait after the new year” mantra, I decided to start writing before the new year, making this a part of 2020 as well. (I am sure my future self will thank me for this decision.) I hope that in 2021, I can become a better writer, which also means a better thinker.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
