<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Life | Bobbie's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2021-05-24T00:05:24-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bowei "Bobbie" Wu .]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Year-long Writing Challenge]]></title>
    <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2021/04/14/year-long-writing-challenge/"/>
    <updated>2021-04-14T19:15:23-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2021/04/14/year-long-writing-challenge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As a “365-day challenge,” I have been doing exercise every day for at least 15 minutes a day since last December, and will continue to do so throughout this year. I have to admit that this feels almost too easy.<sup id="fnref:tough"><a href="#fn:tough" class="footnote">1</a></sup> This is why I am in fact doing another challenge at the same time: to publish at least 40 blog posts this year.</p>

<p>Of course, I won’t publish anything of bad quality by my standard. So this challenge will definitely stretch me to learn and think more regularly, so that I can create something I am happy with every week or so.</p>

<p>On the other hand, publishing 40 articles doesn’t feel overwhelming, which leaves me enough room to work on research projects. A few years ago, I tried blogging on WeChat by setting too ambitious goals. I eventually stopped posting completely after a little more than 10 months; nevertheless, it was a rewarding experience.</p>

<p>With that, I am writing again this year. So far I have been enjoying it and have learned many new things already. Hopefully I won’t blow up my creative engine this time.</p>

<!--more-->

<h3 id="why-write">Why write?</h3>

<p>For a project that lasts as long as a year (or even just a few months), I never rely on willpower to do it. I know myself well enough that I know willpower can only carry me for a few days at best. So I look for motivations that can carry me for as long as I want.</p>

<p>For this year-long writing and publishing challenge, I have had a variety of reasons and desires to do it. I like that when I have many reasons to do something, I will be motivated by at least a few of them on any given day.</p>

<p>Below, I list my reasons to write. Maybe some of them will resonate with somebody who is (considering) writing regularly.</p>

<p><strong>1 Writing changes your life in many different ways.</strong> This is my general feeling about writing, purely emotional and based on my own experience. Twice in my life I had been transformed by writing, the first time during high school and the second time three years ago blogging on WeChat. I used to believe that why you do something should be based on logic, but not anymore. Oftentimes, your emotion and desire are more important – logic can’t explain why we pick certain axioms as the starting point for a mathematical theory, but experience and taste can.</p>

<p><strong>2 Writing distills your existing ideas and make rooms for the new ones.</strong> Every time I have published an article, I feel like I am saving my organized thoughts to a hard drive, so that my brain has more memories to welcome more new ideas. For example, writing “<a href="/blog/2021/04/04/what-is-operational-calculus/"><em>What Is Operational Calculus?</em></a>” had really given me a new insight into the Euler-Maclaurin formula and prepared me to explore its deeper connections with other fields.<sup id="fnref:write-speak"><a href="#fn:write-speak" class="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p><strong>3 Writing gives you a more memorable life.</strong> Do you feel that time slips by so quickly when every day is the same? Writing an essay is like going on an adventure, you will end up changing a lot of your thoughts and discovering ideas you had never expected. When you keep adventuring to different places, at the end of the year you will have so much colorful experience and so many wonderful memories that it feels like you are living a longer life. For example, 2020 might have passed too quick for many people, but it was <a href="/blog/2021/03/12/lockdown-math/">a quality year for me</a>.</p>

<p><strong>4 Writing shifts your focus from <em>problem-solving</em> to <em>understanding</em></strong> because in order to explain something to someone you have to first understand it. Deep understanding is what distinguishes a great mathematician from an okay mathematician.<sup id="fnref:erdos-grothendieck"><a href="#fn:erdos-grothendieck" class="footnote">3</a></sup></p>

<p><strong>5 Writing is embedded in academic lives anyways, why not publish them?</strong> We write research papers, teaching plans, proposals, presentation slides, reviewer reports, email responses. Most of the things we write are unpublished. However, turning some of these writings into publishable articles have generated new ideas for myself. For example, I wrote <a href="/blog/2021/01/30/audience-under-the-lightcone/"><em>Audience Under the Lightcone</em></a> and <a href="/blog/2021/02/14/underestimating-my-ignorance/"><em>Underestimating My Ignorance</em></a> both during my preparations for giving research talks.<sup id="fnref:tao"><a href="#fn:tao" class="footnote">4</a></sup></p>

<p><strong>6 Writing marries different ideas to give birth to new ideas.</strong> For example, <a href="/blog/2021/04/10/questioning-history/"><em>Questioning History</em></a> was a great inspiration to me because it combined education and understanding, two themes I loved to think about, and put them under the framework of history study, which was new to me.</p>

<p><strong>7 Writing absorbs you into a mind-bending field.</strong> Once you start writing, you are transported into an imaginary playground. You will wake up after a writing session realizing that a few hours have passed. It is almost similar to scrolling on social media for a few hours without realizing it; the only difference is that, after a writing session you feel a sense of reward instead of emptyness.</p>

<p><strong>8 Writing regularly gives structure to life.</strong> Doing research alone is not enough for <a href="/blog/2021/01/10/y-combinators-startup-advice-an-academic-perspective/">building an academic career</a>. When I am working on research problems, my mind is often too occupied to think of anything else. Writing regularly gives me the opportunity to ponder on other aspects of my career, such as teaching, networking, and exploring new interests.</p>

<p><strong>9 Writing builds you a radar for detecting good ideas.</strong> Quality input is indispensable to produce quality output. I built the habit of taking notes and jotting down thoughts anytime, so that I don’t lose any sparks that can be turned into an article later. Many of the articles I have written started as quick notes on simple ideas, for example the ideas in <a href="/blog/2021/03/04/your-one-big-desire/"><em>Your One Big Desire</em></a> and <a href="/blog/2021/03/26/it-is-okay-to-speed-up-a-little/"><em>It Is Okay to Speed Up a Little</em></a> both came up when I was focused on unrelated things.</p>

<p>I have more reasons to write than I can list them all here. As I wrote down the list above, more thoughts and inspirations were springing to my mind, I had to put some of them into footnotes so that I didn’t digress. As always, I end up publishing an article with almost no sentence that I originally planned to write. What a journey!</p>

<p>Stay tuned and I will have more to share as I dive into the next adventures.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:tough">
      <p>Of course, I have had a few tougher days, such as the <a href="/blog/2021/01/02/making-small-changes-in-life/">rainy and snowy days</a> and the <a href="/blog/2021/02/22/one-disastrous-week-in-austin/">one disastrous week in Austin</a>; I managed to still exercise on those days. There will be some upcoming challenges as well, like the days after when I will be getting my second dose of COVID vaccine, and days when I will be driving across states. I will see how things go. <a href="#fnref:tough" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:write-speak">
      <p>Writing allows you to discover good ideas because you can spend as much time on each sentence as you want and rewrite as many times as you like. Graham explains this point very well in <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/speak.html"><em>Writing and Speaking</em></a>. <a href="#fnref:write-speak" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:erdos-grothendieck">
      <p>Regarding <em>problem-solving</em> vs <em>understanding</em> in mathematics, I think it is necessary to develop good problem-solving skills, but eventually deep understanding is what is required to do great math. I came across <a href="https://mathoverflow.net/a/7156/110149">this funny quote</a> that expresses exactly this point: “An excellent Erdös might reach certain limits as a mathematician, while a bad Erdös can still be an okay mathematician. On the other hand, a good Grothendieck can be a truly great mathematician, while a bad Grothendieck is really terrible.” <a href="#fnref:erdos-grothendieck" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:tao">
      <p>I think Terry Tao apparently uses the same strategy for blog posting. For example, he must have answered a lot of questions from students and colleagues about mathematical writing, so he had summarized his thoughts on this topic by posting the <a href="https://terrytao.wordpress.com/advice-on-writing-papers/"><em>On writing</em></a> series. <a href="#fnref:tao" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It Is Okay to Speed Up a Little]]></title>
    <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2021/03/26/it-is-okay-to-speed-up-a-little/"/>
    <updated>2021-03-26T00:57:22-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2021/03/26/it-is-okay-to-speed-up-a-little</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We naturally avoid making mistakes. If you were a caveman who survives by hunting, you’d try not to make mistakes that could get you killed by animals.</p>

<p>But in the modern days, we no longer worry about ferocious animals. We now have much safer spaces that are tolerant of our mistakes. So we can afford to make more mistakes. In fact, making mistakes is how we learn.</p>

<p>Yet, people avoid mistakes because it makes you “look bad.” But there is no learning without making mistakes. So how can we gain the courage to learn without worrying about the mistakes we would make?</p>

<p>I think math has the answer.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>In numerical analysis, we design algorithms that solve problems quickly and accurately. One major task when developing such an algorithm is to combat with numerical errors. If you open any classical numerical analysis textbook, you will likely see discussions of error analysis: how to eliminate or reduce roundoff errors, and how to prevent errors from propagating and contaminating the final results.</p>

<p>Talking about errors can sound bad and boring. It may drive beginners away from numerical analysis before they can learn the true beauty of the subject.</p>

<p>In fact, mathematicians know about the bad connotations associated with “errors.” When communicating with fellow mathematicians, we don’t talk about errors as often as one would imagine. For example, instead of saying “the algorithm makes smaller errors” we like to say “the algorithm converges faster.” And instead of “the algorithm prevents error propagation” we like to say “the algorithm is stable and robust.”</p>

<p>“Fast convergence” and “smaller errors” mean the same thing, but the framings are completely different. “Convergence” focuses on the positive effects and makes people excited. If you ask any numerical analyst what makes them love their field, I’ll bet you no one would say they love the error analysis; rather, they would tell you about the lightning computation speeds, the simple ideas behind powerful algorithms, the unexpected connections between ideas from different fields, and more.</p>

<p>Likewise, “making mistakes” gets its own bad rap. I propose replacing it with “speeding up” because making more mistakes allows you to learn quicker. Whenever you are stuck and can’t make any progress because you are afraid of making mistakes, try to tell yourself “I am just going to speed up my learning a little.”</p>

<p>Making mistakes can be embarrassing, but <a href="https://twitter.com/edlatimore/status/1058305553020141570">embarrassment is simply the cost of entry</a>. The embarrassment you feel only exist in your mind, learning is what can actually happen. Once you allow yourself to look stupid and take on the beginner’s mindset, learning will be unstoppable.</p>

<p>Make more mistakes. It is okay to speed up a little, and it feels great.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lockdown Math]]></title>
    <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2021/03/12/lockdown-math/"/>
    <updated>2021-03-12T01:28:25-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2021/03/12/lockdown-math</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the <a href="/blog/2021/03/04/your-one-big-desire">previous post</a> I talked about anxiety caused by things that you actually have control over. This time I’d like to also touch on situations that you can’t really change, such as a pandemic.</p>

<p>A pandemic makes people anxious because it freezes life. A lot of activities have to be suspended. You can’t do what you would normally do. You don’t know how long the pandemic would last — probably a few months, probably a few years. All you can do is wait, indefinitely.</p>

<h3 id="mathematicians-in-confinement">Mathematicians in confinement</h3>

<p>Some groups of people seem to be doing quite well in a lockdown situation. Mathematicians happen to be one such group.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>Sophus Lie, who established <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lie_algebra">Lie algebra</a> during his imprisonment, said that “a mathematician is comparatively well suited to be in prison.” And Lie was not alone, 70 years later another great mathematician, André Weil, who also had a productive time in prison, wondered “if it’s only in prison that I work so well, will I have to arrange to spend two or three months locked up every year?”</p>

<p>According to the fun article <a href="http://www.nieuwarchief.nl/serie5/pdf/naw5-2020-21-2-095.pdf"><em>Lockdown Mathematics</em></a>, both Lie and Weil were mistaken for spies during wartimes “due to their strange habits as eccentric mathematicians who incessantly scribbled some sort of incomprehensible notes and wandered in nature without any credible purpose discernible to outsiders.”</p>

<p>There are many other interesting examples from that article. The bottom line is, many mathematicians have experienced highly productive periods during confinement situations, where they were free of distractions and could focus deeply on their thoughts; although in some cases, this effect only lasted for a month or two, eventually the productivity boost waned. After all, mathematicians are still humans who need some breaks.</p>

<p>I have to say that the above description perfectly summarized my experience during the COVID lockdown. I was super productive and wrote two papers during the first few months of the lockdown, then I started to get distracted and wanted to socialize again.</p>

<p>Now it is March again, an anniversary of the COVID lockdown in the US. Maybe I could also benefit from setting up a few months of faux lockdown for myself every year.</p>

<h3 id="flow-vs-pandemic">Flow v.s. Pandemic</h3>

<p>According to some <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0242043">recent research</a>, getting in the state of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flow_(psychology)">flow</a> might be one best way to cope with lockdown anxieties. When you are experiencing flow, you are deeply focused on something; time seems to slip by quickly, a few hours feel like just a moment to you.</p>

<p>Not just mathematicians, other people find their flow in all sorts of ways: painting, making handicrafts, reading books, writing essays, coding. So when you get into flow, not only that time passes much quicker, but you are also accomplishing something meaningful to you. It just completely flips the lockdown situation around and gives you a positive experience.</p>

<p>In fact, this experience may have deeper implications if we redefine “pandemic” as a state of mind:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A “pandemic” is an extended period during which you are constantly anxious about one thing that you can’t control.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>By this definition, people are constantly undergoing all kinds of pandemics: losing jobs, struggling to graduate, accumulating debts, being homesick, feeling lonely. In each of these cases, people are stuck in a “personal pandemic” that they can’t easily escape and have to live with it for an uncertain amount of time.</p>

<p>Inspired by the lockdown experience, maybe one solution to a “personal pandemic” is to accept it like we accepted that we would be living under COVID for a few years, and turn to focus on something we truly care about. Oftentimes, the consequence of a “personal pandemic” is not as dire as one might think it would be; a threat might also be an opportunity for growth. So being able to find your flow could carry you through the most difficult time of your “personal pandemic,” giving you the chance to come out stronger and better off.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Your One Big Desire]]></title>
    <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2021/03/04/your-one-big-desire/"/>
    <updated>2021-03-04T23:23:03-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2021/03/04/your-one-big-desire</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Anxiety comes from desire. You are anxious when you desire something but not sure if you can get it.</p>

<h4 id="linear-independence-of-desires">Linear Independence of Desires</h4>

<p>I’d like to see different desires as being <em>linearly independent</em>.</p>

<p><strong>Linearity.</strong> When you have many desires, they “superpose” to increase your level of anxiety. For example, if someone wants to be rich, be famous, to have a superb partner, and to be playing all day and not have to work … all at the same time, then this must be the most anxious person in the world.</p>

<p><strong>Independence.</strong> Whether or not one desire is satisfied doesn’t affect your ability to satisfy another desire. For example, you don’t have to be rich to start doing things you like, you don’t have to be gorgeous to start building a good relationship, you don’t have to be the most intelligent person to be confident.</p>

<p>As a corollary, if you just give up most of your desires, you will stop being overly anxious and have much more energy to persue your most important desire.</p>

<!--more-->

<h4 id="pick-one-desire-and-enjoy-life">Pick One Desire and Enjoy Life</h4>

<p>My last year of PhD was an incredible year for me. But I actually failed to graduate the year before. I spent some hard time with myself in the summer and decided that I would try to achieve one big goal in my final year: to graduate as a <em>competent</em> scholar. I picked this goal because I wouldn’t be satisfied with <em>just</em> graduating and then spend my time working on some random job just to get by. I truely hoped to still be able to enjoy doing creative work after graduation.</p>

<p>To achieve this goal, my logic was plain and simple: I need to be productive to be competent for my work; I need to be healthy to be productive. So I started eating healthier and exercising more regularly.</p>

<p>Interestingly, as I became a healthier person, I also began to enjoy life. Over the year, besides focusing on my work, I also had a very supportive relationship and became a more grateful person, which in turn made me a more confident person and helped me build new connections. In the end, I had not only graduated, but also delivered a speech at the commencement and found a job I liked which allowed me to continue to do creative work.</p>

<p>I am sure a lot of these results were just luck, but it was fascinating how the world seemed to be coordinating to send me through an upward spiral.</p>

<p>I have learned two things from this experience:<br />
(1) I don’t really need a lot of grit or perseverance to achieve something. All I need to do is let go of all the other desires, then I have plenty of mental power to work on the one big thing.<br />
(2) Letting go of other desires doesn’t mean I won’t be doing all those things. It just means that I don’t see them as “goals.” For example, I was eating healthy food and exercising regularly only because I enjoyed them, I didn’t have to do them if I thought they made me feel worse.</p>

<h4 id="your-one-big-desire">Your One Big Desire</h4>

<p>There was one quote that I thought was very beautiful but which had never really believed:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When you want something, all the universe conspires in helping you to achieve it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This was from the fiction <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Alchemist_(novel)"><em>The Alchemist</em></a> by Paulo Coello. Behind this quote was one of the most romantic stories I have ever read. So romantic that I never thought reality would work that way.</p>

<p>However, since then I have had this “something” that I truely wanted for a few times (although each time it lasted only for a year or two). Each time I made up my mind, I had this peculiar feeling that the world did seem to be helping me out in unexpected ways. These experiences had pushed me to read between the lines. I am realizing that maybe this “something” in the quote has to be singular. It must be the one thing that you absolutely want during that period of your life, from which you won’t get distracted by anything else. In a world full of uncertainties, this one desire can be the very certainty that guides you through chaos and doubts.</p>

<p>What is the one desire that is truely important to you? It is okay that you are anxious about that one and only that one.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One Disastrous Week in Austin &mdash; We Survived]]></title>
    <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2021/02/22/one-disastrous-week-in-austin/"/>
    <updated>2021-02-22T01:51:51-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2021/02/22/one-disastrous-week-in-austin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>80+ hours. I can’t remember the last time I have been without power at subzero temperature for this long.</p>

<p>Austin (and Texas) just went through a disaster. A winter storm devoured the city, turning it into a frozen world for a week. On Monday, January 15, 2021, temperature dropped below -10°C, coldest over the past century. Snow was thick enough to sink your entire boots in. While such cold weather is nothing special in northern states like Michigan, it is nothing the Texans have ever seen. The electricity infrastructures in Texas were absolutely unprepared for such extreme condition, leaving millions of people out of power throughout the week.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, I am one of the witnesses and sufferers in this historic event. To make things worse, both of the kitchen stove and hot water in my apartment rely on electricity, so we are out of every possible source of energy.</p>

<p>Long story short, we survived. And here is how.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>First of all, I am thankful to have been staying with my girlfriend this year. The support and encouragement we provide to each other is the most important reason that we stayed positive and endured this hardship. It is true that a long-term relationship compounds its value over time and can be your lifesaver in unexpected events.</p>

<p>Second of all, getting helps from our neighbors was the silver lining during the week. After a day without power and heat, I started asking around for help on my phone. Eventually, I was connected to a friend’s friend who lived nearby and was fortunate enough to still have power in their building. It was also important that we could just walk there because you don’t want to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/02/11/us/fort-worth-wreck.html">drive on icy roads</a> in such weather. So from Wednesday on, we could have something hot to eat for lunch and bring some hot water home. I sent food pictures to my family far away so that they knew I was doing fine.</p>

<p>Preparation also made a difference. We stocked up some food before the week because we paid attention to the weather forecast. This turned out to be one of our best decisions because later in the week we didn’t have to stand in the cold in long lines outside of HEB. Ironically, the freezing temperature helped preserve our food during the week-long power outage.</p>

<p>Daily activities became simple. We went to bed before 9 PM because there is nothing much you can do in a cold dark night. We had more than 12 hours of sleep every day to save energy and stay warm. During the day, when we were not busy surviving, we spent most of our time reading which distracted us from the frigid reality. I also did exercises and lifted weights at home, which I think is an acceptable compromise for my <a href="/blog/2021/01/02/making-small-changes-in-life/">365-day challenge</a> since it was unsafe to be running outside.</p>

<p>The weather warmed up towards the weekend, finally above freezing on Friday. Our building got its electricity back on Friday afternoon and it had been more than 80 hours since we lost power.</p>

<p>Looking back, I think it is equally important to survive both the physical and mental challenges. I can’t imagine what it would be like if I were enduring all this all by myself and had no one to talk to. Staying calm and positive during a hard time can make a huge difference. Once you have hope, the physical challenges look easier to defeat. I wish everybody who suffered the power outage during this brutal week had found someone they can reach out to.</p>

<p>As the driving condition was improved, we went to stay at our friends’ house during the weekend. Because of COVID, it’s been a long time since we could spend a day or two with people we care about. I feel grateful that a harsh situation like this became the best opportunity to bond again.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
