<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Fluid-dynamics | Bobbie's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/categories/fluid-dynamics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-11-12T18:48:52-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bowei "Bobbie" Wu .]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fluid or Solid?]]></title>
    <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2016/09/13/fluid-or-solid/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-13T20:26:57-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2016/09/13/fluid-or-solid</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is something I learned today from the Fluid Mechanics class in the Chemical Engineering department, class number CHE 527.</p>

<p>We have had the intuitive ideas about what a fluid is versus what a solid is. A solid is something that can resist shear stress, and will maintain its shape, while a fluid is something that will deform continuously when a shear is applied to it, without changing back to the original shape.</p>

<p>But there are many substances in the world that cannot be classified into solid or fluid with the above simple and intuitive definitions. Here are some examples:</p>

<h4 id="silly-putty">Silly putty:</h4>

<!--more-->

<p><img src="/images/blog_figures/Silly_Putty.jpg" width="200"></p>

<p>The silly putty is a moldable toy that you can stretch and shape it into any shapes. With a glance it looks like a solid, does not seem to flow like a fluid, and you may even bounce it like a ball. But this is only true in short term, if you put in a container and give it a rest, in long term it will start to look like a fluid; the piece of silly putty will flow (slowly) and eventually take the shape of the container.</p>

<h4 id="mayonnaise">Mayonnaise:</h4>

<p><img src="/images/blog_figures/mayonnaise.jpg" width="200"></p>

<p>Mayonnaise is a comment condiment. If a lump of mayo sits there, it won’t flow and will stay as it is, like solid would do. But if the same lump of mayo is sheared by a small (but big enough) stress, it will start to deform continuously like a fluid and never come back to the initial shape. (Toothpaste has the similar property.)</p>

<h4 id="orbitz-a-drink">Orbitz (a drink)</h4>

<p><img src="/images/blog_figures/orbitz.jpg" width="200"></p>

<p>The Orbitz was once a popular beverage. Inside the transparent drink you can see some little solid “beads” suspended in the fluid. A remarkable fact is that although the “beads” have different density than the fluid, will neither sink nor rise and will just stay in the same position provided the bottle of drink is put stationary. On the other hand, if you simply give the bottle a shake, the beads will start flowing (swimming) around right away, making it obvious that the drink is a fluid. The reason behind this is that, the fluid in the bottle is somehow like the mayonnaise, it requires a certain (small but big enough) shear stress to flow like a fluid, otherwise it just stay put like a solid; the bare gravitational force is not enough to move the fluid.</p>

<p>Glass, on the other hand, is not strictly a solid. The glass has relatively small viscosity in high temperature and can flow like honey, in low temperature the glass will become (much) harder to deform, but nevertheless can be essentially treated as a “fluid” with super high viscosity.</p>

<p>In summary, we have come to the funny conclusion that <strong>the Orbitz beverage technically consists of a fluid container (the glass bottle) holding a solid (the drink) inside.</strong></p>

<h4 id="corn-starch">Corn starch:</h4>

<p><img src="/images/blog_figures/Tara-Corn-Starch.jpg" width="400"></p>

<p>Like silly putty, the corn starch when subject to sudden and huge impact will behave like a solid; you can even walk on a pool of corn starch (shown in the picture) as long as you move fast enough. But if you move slowly in this pool (i.e. shearing the corn starch slowly), it starts to behave like a fluid and sinks you inside.</p>

<p>All these examples remind us that we need to re-think our (intuitive) definitions for fluid and solid. Strictly speaking, nothing in this world is completely a solid or fluid, but there exists a spectrum between the two extreme states, some substances are more fluidlike while some others are more solidlike.</p>

<p>Let’s summarize with a verse in the Bible: “The mountains flowed before the Lord” - prophet Deborah (Judges 5:5).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dimensional Analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2016/08/11/dimensional-analysis/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-11T16:00:40-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2016/08/11/dimensional-analysis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Once one of my engineering friends asked me: “Why would you need all these dimensionless numbers? There are so many of them and they just complicate stuff!”</p>

<p>If something is not useful, it wouldn’t have been invented in science; this is particularly true for dimensional analysis which has made great success across all fields of science.</p>

<p>To put things simple, dimensional analysis has two major fundamental applications:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Simplify equations and lead to new scientific branches/specialties.</li>
  <li>Guide scientific experiments with dynamic similitude.</li>
</ul>

<!--more-->

<h4 id="simplification-of-the-navier-stokes-equation">Simplification of the Navier-Stokes equation</h4>

<p>Look at the Navier-Stokes equation</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">\rho \left(\frac{\partial \mathbf{u}}{\partial t} + \mathbf{u}\cdot\nabla\mathbf{u}\right) = -\nabla p + \mu\Delta \mathbf{u} + \rho\mathbf{g}</script>

<p>At a particular point in a flow, We may find that some term in this equation is <em>orders of magnitude</em> bigger than others. We could simplify the N-S equation by retaining those terms that matter, and eliminating those that don’t.</p>

<p>How do we go about to eliminate the negligible terms? To put the conclusion first, the magnitudes of each term in the N-S equation depend on both the <strong>sturcture</strong> of the flow and <strong>location</strong> in the flow – with appropriate flow structure and at appropriate location, one can safely delete certain terms in the N-S equation. This whole process of simplfying the equations, is called <strong>dimensional analysis</strong>.</p>

<h4 id="dimensional-analysis">Dimensional analysis</h4>

<p>There are three steps in performing dimensional analysis.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Identify <strong>characteristic scales</strong> of a flow.
    <ul>
      <li>characteristic length $L$ is related to the size of the boundaries</li>
      <li>characteristic velocity $U$ is determined by the particular mechanism driving the flow</li>
      <li>characteristic time $T$ is either imposed by external means or simply defined as $T=L/U$.</li>
    </ul>

    <blockquote>
      <p>For example:</p>

      <ol>
        <li>In the case of unidirectional flow through channel: $U = $ max velocity across channel.</li>
        <li>In the case of uniform flow past stationary body: $U = $ velocity of the incident flow, $L =$ diameter of the body.</li>
        <li>In the case of forced oscillatory flow: $T = $ period of oscillation.</li>
      </ol>
    </blockquote>
  </li>
  <li><em>Nondimensionalization</em>:
    <ul>
      <li>Rescale each variable in the equation into a dimensionless variable. 
 <script type="math/tex">\hat{\mathbf{u}}:=\frac{\mathbf{u}}{U},\qquad \hat{\mathbf{x}}:=\frac{\mathbf{x}}{L},\qquad \hat{t}:=\frac{t}{T},\qquad \hat{p}:=\frac{pL}{\mu U}.</script></li>
      <li>Rewrite the equation into a dimensionless form.
 <script type="math/tex">\beta \frac{\partial \hat{\mathbf{u}}}{\partial \hat{t}} + \mbox{Re}\,\hat{\mathbf{u}}\cdot\hat{\nabla}\hat{\mathbf{u}} = -\hat{\nabla} \hat{p} + \hat{\nabla}^2 \hat{\mathbf{u}} + \frac{\mbox{Re}}{\mbox{Fr}^2}\frac{\mathbf{g}}{g}</script></li>
      <li>The multiplication factors of each term are nondimensional groups, called <em>dimensionless numbers</em>
        <ul>
          <li>Frequency parameter: $\beta:=\frac{L^2}{\nu T}$, expresses the relative magnitudes of the inertial acceleration force and the viscous force</li>
          <li>Reynolds number: $\mbox{Re}:=\frac{UL}{\nu}$, expresses the relative magnitudes of the inertia convective force and the viscous force</li>
          <li>Froude number: $\mbox{Fr}:=\frac{U}{\sqrt{gL}}$ expresses the relative magnitudes of the inertial convective force and the body force</li>
          <li>The group $\frac{\mbox{Re}}{\mbox{Fr}^2}=\frac{gL^2}{\nu U}$, expresses the relative magnitudes of the body force and the viscous force</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Eliminate the dominated terms.
    <ul>
      <li>If $\mbox{Re}\ll 1$ and $\beta\ll1$, the dominant terms give <strong>Stokes equation</strong>
 <script type="math/tex">-\nabla p + \mu \nabla^2\mathbf{u}+ \rho\mathbf{g}=\mathbf{0}</script>
 where the inertia terms go away, resulting in a quasi-steady fluid.</li>
      <li>If $\mbox{Re}\gg 1$ and $\beta\gg1$, and rescale the pressure by $\hat{p}=\frac{p}{\rho U^2}$ instead, the dominant terms give <strong>Euler’s equation</strong>
 <script type="math/tex">\rho \left(\frac{\partial \mathbf{u}}{\partial t} + \mathbf{u}\cdot\nabla\mathbf{u}\right) = -\nabla p + \rho\mathbf{g}</script>
 where the viscous term goes away, making it behave like an inviscid fluid.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<h4 id="dynamic-similitude">Dynamic similitude</h4>

<p>TBA.</p>

<h5 id="reference">Reference:</h5>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Introduction-Theoretical-Computational-Fluid-Dynamics/dp/0199752079">Pozrikidis C. (2011). Introduction to Theoretical and Computational Fluid Dynamics (2nd ed.). Oxford University Press.</a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
