<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Math | Bobbie's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/categories/math/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-09-14T13:39:13-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bowei "Bobbie" Wu .]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Holy Trinity]]></title>
    <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2017/05/19/the-holy-trinity/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-19T22:03:22-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2017/05/19/the-holy-trinity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This isn’t about theology, but I will talk about the number three.</p>

<p>We love the number three. Many of our rules/doctrines consist of three parts. For example, in Christianity, there is the theory of the Holy Trinity, stating that God manifests Himself in three forms: the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit. I’d love to cast them into a shamrock diagram:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/blog_figures/shamrock_holy.png" width="300"></p>

<p>The key idea here is that, although there are three forms, there is really only one God.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>While I am not a Theologist, I appreciate the idea that an important concept is broken into three aspects, each of them stems from the same root, and connects with each other to promote deeper understanding of the subject. Let’s call them the “shamrock ideas”.</p>

<p>I happened to have encountered some of the interesting and beautiful shamrock ideas in the realm of science and mathematics. These ideas have given me incredible insights into subjects, helping me see the big pictures of a lot of seemingly scattered knowledge.</p>

<h2 id="science">Science</h2>

<p>Perhaps the most well-known example of a shamrock idea is the three components of science.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There are three great branches of modern science: theory, experiment, and computation.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/blog_figures/shamrock_science.png" width="300"></p>

<p>The keyword in this shamrock is <em>computation</em>, it reminds us how computation has influenced science, and has evolved from a mere tool into a full-fledged scientific branch.</p>

<p>In the early days of science, machines were invented to help scientists with their calculations. Searching the internet you will find calculators like Arithmometer (1850s-1910s) and Comptometer (1880s-1970s). Those machines can add, subtract, multiply and divide numbers. They were once very useful to scientists, and are now all gone to museums. In the mid-1900s, electronic computers started to take over, and computing power skyrocketed in the past 60 years. Computer performance evolved from hectoscale computing (~200 operations per second) with the first IBM computer in 1946, to petascale computing in 2009 with modern supercomputers, which is thousands of trillions of operations per second.</p>

<p>Such leap in computing power has unleashed ideas that were sheer impossible just decades ago.</p>

<p>With experiment, science have gone a long way tracing back to the ancient Greeks. With computation, science has taken off and is moving ever faster. We can simulate thins that are too far (universe), too small (quantum), too expensive (medicine), or too complex (social network).</p>

<h2 id="mathematics">Mathematics</h2>

<p>I would like to mention more shamrock ideas I found reading math.</p>

<h3 id="functions-boyd">Functions <sup id="fnref:boyd"><a href="#fn:boyd" class="footnote">1</a></sup></h3>

<p>The function shamrock has three leaves respectively labeled formula, spectral coefficients, and grid point values. Together, these three concepts help us better understand and use functions. To see how these three concepts connect to each other, we realize that we go from the symbolic $f(x)$ to values ${f_j}$ by sampling, from $f(x)$ to spectral coefficients ${a_j}$ by integral transforms (e.g. Fourier transform), and from ${f_j}$ to ${a_j}$ by discrete algorithms (e.g. FFT).</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/blog_figures/shamrock_function.png" width="300"></p>

<p>When solving a problem that involves a function $f(x)$, the symbolic formula is manipulated with analytical methods, its spectral coefficients are useful for Galerkin methods, and the grid point values are what the convenient pseudospectral methods operate on.</p>

<p>A mathematician would be crippled if failing to understand and to freely switch between any of them.</p>

<h3 id="analysis-trefethen">Analysis <sup id="fnref:trefethen"><a href="#fn:trefethen" class="footnote">2</a></sup></h3>

<p>This probably is my favorite shamrock. In analysis, the three types of series, Fourier, Laurent, and Chebyshev, are really the same series looking from different angles.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/blog_figures/shamrock_analysis.png" width="300"></p>

<p>Let’s consider the substitutions</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">x = \frac{z+z^{-1}}{2} = \cos\theta</script>

<p>they give the equivalent relations</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">T_n(x) = \frac{z^n+z^{-n}}{2} = \cos(n\theta)</script>

<p>where $T_n(x)$ is the Chebyshev polynomial of order $n$. Given a smooth function $f(x)$ on $x\in[-1,1]$, it can be expanded as a Chebyshev series</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">f(x) = \sum^\infty_{n=0}a_nT_n(x)</script>

<p>which under the equivalent relations gives</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">\sum^\infty_{n=0}a_nT_n(x) = \sum^\infty_{n=0} a_n \frac{z^n+z^{-n}}{2} = \sum^\infty_{n=0} a_n \cos(n\theta)</script>

<p>or</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">\sum^\infty_{n=0}a_nT_n(x) = \frac{a_0}{2}+\frac{1}{2}\sum^\infty_{n=-\infty} a_{|n|} z^n = \frac{a_0}{2}+\frac{1}{2}\sum^\infty_{n=-\infty} a_{|n|} e^{in\theta}</script>

<p>The last equalities show the amazing relationships between the three branches of analysis, providing a picture about how viewing from different angles gives you different series expansions:</p>

<ul>
  <li>If you look at the unit circle in the complex plane (or a periodic interval) $\theta\in[0,2\pi]$, you see Fourier series, the fundamental tool for real analysis</li>
  <li>If you look at the annulus <span>$\frac{1}{\rho} &lt; |z| &lt; \rho$</span>, you see Laurent series, the fundamental tool for complex analysis</li>
  <li>If you look at the interval $x\in[-1,1]$, you see Chebyshev series, the fundamental tool for numerical analysis</li>
</ul>

<p>Such connections are always there, but you need to discover them. Even many math majors know little about the shamrock, and most of them have taken all three courses.</p>

<h2 id="a-final-note">A final note</h2>

<p>I love the shamrocks not because they teach me new concepts; in fact they don’t. I have understood the concepts in the three leaves of each shamrock before I saw them put together. The important thing of these shamrocks is that they provide a unified view, a new prospective that connects and sees things you knew differently. Like Kalid Azad (author of <a href="https://betterexplained.com">BetterExplained</a>) once <a href="https://betterexplained.com/articles/learn-math-like-mega-man/">mentioned in a post</a>, our understandings improve the most not when we’ve learned new concepts, but when mindset shifts happen.</p>

<h3 id="references">References:</h3>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:boyd">
      <p>John P Boyd, <em>Chebyshev and Fourier Spectral Methods</em>, Section 9.3 <a href="#fnref:boyd" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:trefethen">
      <p>Nick Trefethen, <em>Approximation Theory and Approximation Practice</em>, Chapter 3 <a href="#fnref:trefethen" class="reversefootnote">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Human Brain Works Logarithmically]]></title>
    <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2016/09/12/human-brain-works-logarithmically/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-12T11:20:24-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2016/09/12/human-brain-works-logarithmically</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Do you know that our brain works logarithmically?</em></p>

<ol>
  <li>Do this exercise:
    <ul>
      <li>Draw a number line</li>
      <li>Mark $0$ and $1,000,000,000$ on the line.</li>
      <li>Ask yourself a question: where is $1,000$?</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Many people put $1,000$ at the $1/3$ position. Note that $1,000=10^3$, $1,000,000,000=10^9$, where $9$ is triple of $3$. This implies that we perceive number logarithmically!</li>
  <li>Not only <strong>size</strong> of a number, but also <strong>weight</strong> of an object, <strong>loudness</strong> of a sound, <strong>brightness</strong> of a star, <strong>spiciness</strong> of a chili, all of these are perceived logarithmically by the human brain.</li>
  <li>Such logarithmic law is known more than 100 years ago, under the name “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weber%E2%80%93Fechner_law"><strong>Weber-Fechner law</strong></a>” in psychophysics.</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[数学是发明还是发现]]></title>
    <link href="http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2016/08/25/shu-xue-shi-fa-ming-huan-shi-fa-xian/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-25T10:21:23-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bobbielf2.github.io/blog/2016/08/25/shu-xue-shi-fa-ming-huan-shi-fa-xian</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>“<strong>亚里士多德阵营</strong>”支持数学来源于实践，是发明：</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>数学学是人类探索自然的经验抽象，是人类的发明；数学思想必须与现实经验结合才有其存在的价值。</p>
</blockquote>

<p>“<strong>柏拉图阵营</strong>”认为数学存在于理想世界，人只是发现它：</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>人类的数学思想是理念世界在人类意识中的投射，是人类的发现；理念世界有其自身的特质和变化，并非现实经验的简单抽象。</p>
</blockquote>

<p>其实，数学既是发现，也是发明。关键在于人类的智力发展出抽象能力，在发现的基础上进行发明。我属于“<strong>克罗内克阵营</strong>”：</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>上帝创造了整数，其余都是人的工作。</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
